Saleem Raza

Curriculum Vitae

Flat No. 130, First Floor, Ali Twin Tower, Hussainabad, Hyderabad, Sindh, 71000, Pakistan
☐ +92 3010259379
☑ saleem.raza@daad-alumni.de
ⓒ saleemrazam.github.io
in saleem-raza-phd-13035b30/
ⓒ saleemrazam



Research Interests

An independent and self-motivated researcher and academician with more than 12 years of experience spanning electronic, telecom, and computer networks. My passion for teaching and research is reflected through my achievements, I am truly believer that teaching and research can bring about progressive changes in society.

Professional and Research Experience

2024 – date **Assistant Professor**, *The University of Larkano*, *Pakistan*, **Teaching:** Electronics and Telecommunication

2013 – 2023 **Assistant Professor**, *Quaid-e-Awam University of Engineering, Science & Technology, Pakistan*, **Teaching:** Electronics and Telecommunication, (I was on PhD study leave to Germany during job)

2016 – 2020 **PhD Candidate**, *Otto-von-Guericke University Magdeburg, Germany*, **Research areas:** Computer Communication and Wireless Networks

2014 – 2016 **PhD Candidate**, *University of Münster, Germany*,

Research areas: Computer Communication and Wireless Networks

2011 - 2013 Lecturer, Sukkur IBA Community College, Naushahro Feroze, Pakistan,

Teaching: Electronics and Computer Science, and Tutorials

2007 – 2010 Executive Engineer Field Support WiMAX Networks,

Responsibilities: Field activities related to installation, configuration, testing, and maintenance of the WiMAX networks at customer and corporate side.

Education

2014 – 2020 Ph.D Computer Science, Otto-von-Guericke University Magdeburg, Germany,

Dissertation title: "Medium Access Control Protocols for Reliable Communication in Low-Power Industrial Applications"

2009 – 2012 M.E Electronic Systems Engineering, (CGPA 3.37, (v.good)), Mehran University of Engineering & Technology, Pakistan

Thesis title: "WiMAX Femtocells Solutions, Strengths and Challenges"

2010 – 2011 **Erasmus Mundus (exchange student during masters)**, Communication, Media and Information (one semester) *Technologies, Aalborg University, Copenhagen, Denmark*

2002 – 2006 **B.E Electronic Engineering**, *(CGPA 3.68 (v.good))*, Mehran University of Engineering and Technology, Pakistan

Thesis title: "Analysis of GSM Network and Radio Path Loss"

Supervision

I have the privilege to supervise several undergraduate final year projects as follows

- 2023 Design and Development of IoT Enabled Smart Car Parking System
- 2022 IoT-based Smart Home Using LoRa
- 2021 Face Detection Attendance System using Raspberry pi

2015 The importance of the MAC layer for the vision of the Tactile Internet

Expertise and Skills (Intermediate, Basic)

Programming C++ Object Oriented Programming, C, and Python (MatplotLib, Pyplot, Pandas, Pygal, NumPy),

Linux shell scripting

Simulation OMNet++, Contiki-OS/Cooja

Basic hardware Raspberry Pi, Arduino, ESP-32

Miscellaneous LaTeX/Overleaf, Inkscape, Subversion, GIT, Linux (Ubuntu Debian), Windows-OS, & Mac-OS

Awards, Grants, and Scholarships

2019 Scholarship, STiBET DAAD for 3 months grant for completing the remaining my PhD research

2019 Recipient of the HEC travel grant for paper presentation at the CCNC 2019, USA

2018 scholarship, STiBET DAAD for 3 months grant for completing the remaining my PhD

2017 Best Paper Award, for VEHICULAR 2017 conference paper, IARIA conference

2010 scholarship, Erasmus Mundus Mobility for Life,6 months research stay at Aalborg University Copenhagen, Denmark

Publications

Journals

- 2024 Muhammad Zawish, Fayaz Ali Dharejo, Sunder Ali Khowaja, **Saleem Raza,** Steven Davy, Kapal Dev, and Paolo Bellavista "Al and 6G Into the Metaverse: Fundamentals, Challenges and Future Research Trends". *IEEE Open Journal of the Communications Society (2024), (Impact factor: 6.3)*
- 2023 Weizheng Wang, Zhaoyang Han, Thippa Reddy Gadekallu, **Saleem Raza**, Jawad Tanveer and Chunhua Su "Lightweight Blockchain-Enhanced Mutual Authentication Protocol for UAVs". **IEEE Internet of Things Journal (2023), (Impact factor: 10.6)**
- Sunder Ali Khowaja, Parus Khuwaja, Fayaz Ali Dharejo, **Saleem Raza**, Ik Hyun Lee, Rizwan Ali Naqvi, Kapal Dev "ReFuSeAct: Representation fusion using self-supervised learning for activity recognition in next generation networks". **International Journal on Multi-Sensor, Multi-Source Information Fusion (2023), (Impact factor: 18.6)**
- 2023 AshuTaneja, Shalli Rani, **Saleem Raza**, Amar Jain, & Shebnam M. Sefat. "Energy efcient IRS assisted 6G network for Industry 5.0". **Scientific Reports (2023), (Impact factor: 4.6)**
- 2023 Shah Zeb, Muhammad Ahmad Rathore, Syed Ali Hassan, **Saleem Raza**, Kapal Dev, Giancarlo Fortino. "Towards Al-enabled NextG Networks with Edge Intelligence-assisted Microservice Orchestration". **IEEE Wireless Communications (2023), (Impact factor: 12.9)**
- 2023 Aneela Pathan, Tayab D. Memon, Saleem Raza, Rizwan Aziz. "An autocorrelation-less single-bit Weiner filter on FPGA". Journal of Biomedical Signal Processing and Control (2023), (Impact factor: 5.1)
- 2023 Shalli Rani, Divya, Gupta, **Saleem Raza**, Nawab Muhammad Faseeh Qureshi, Romany F. Mansour, Mahmoud Ragabd. "Security Paradigm for Remote Health Monitoring Edge Devices in Internet of Things". **Journal of King Saud University Computer and Information Sciences 2023** (2023), (Impact factor: 8.839)
- 2020 Faheem, Muhammad, Rizwan Aslam Butt, Basit Raza, Hani Alquhayz, Muhammad Waqar Ashraf, Saleem Raza, and MD Asri Bin Ngadi. "FFRP: dynamic firefly mating optimization inspired energy efficient routing protocol for internet of underwater wireless sensor networks". IEEE Access 8 (2020): pp.39587-39604, (Impact factor: 3.367)

- 2019 Raza, Saleem, Muhammad Faheem, and Mesut Guenes. "Industrial wireless sensor and actuator networks in industry 4.0: Exploring requirements, protocols, and challenges—A MAC survey". International Journal of Communication Systems 32, no. 15 (2019): e4074. (Impact factor: 2.047)
- 2018 Nikoukar, Ali, **Saleem Raza**, Angelina Poole, Mesut Güneş, and Behnam Dezfouli. "Low-power wireless for the internet of things: Standards and applications".**IEEE Access 6 (2018): pp.67893-67926. (Impact factor: 3.367)**

Conferences

- 2020 Nikoukar, Ali, **Saleem Raza**, Tharakeswara Rao, Mesut Güneş, and Behnam Dezfouli. "Service Migrations in TSCH Network using Wireless Channel Estimation and Prediction." **INFORMATIK 2020 (2021).**
- 2019 Raza, Saleem, Tim van Der Lee, George Exarchakos, and Mesut Güneş. "A reliability analysis of TSCH protocol in a mobile scenario." In 2019 16th IEEE Annual Consumer Communications & Networking Conference (CCNC), pp. 1-6. IEEE, 2019.
- 2018 Raza, Saleem, Alfonso Ariza Quintana, Adarsh Agnihotri, Behnam Dezfouli, and Mesut Güneş. "Dual-Mode Time-Slotted (DMTS) MAC Protocol for Industrial Control Applications." In 2018 IEEE GLOBECOM Workshops (GC Wkshps), pp. 1-6. IEEE, 2018.
- van der Lee, Tim, **Saleem Raza**, George Exarchakos, and Mesut Gunes. "Towards co-located TSCH networks: An inter-network interference perspective." **In 2018 IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM)**, pp. 1-6. **IEEE**, 2018.

Scientific Activities

Memberships

2019 - present IEEE ComSoc, Member IEEE, Internet of Things, Member

2007 - present Pakistan Engineering Council, Member

External Reviewer

Conferences IEEE PIMRC, GLOBECOM, Med-Hoc-Net, WTS, CCNC

Journals IEEE Access, IEEE Network Magazine, IEEE Journal of Internet Technology, International Journal Communication Systems (Wiley), Journal of Future Generation Computer Systems (Elsevier), Adhoc-networks (Elsevier), BS/BE, MS/ME and PhD thesis Evaluator

Languages

English (fluent), Urdu (fluent), Sindhi (native), German (beginner)

Interests and Hobbies

Reading magazine/books/newspapers, playing cricket, photography, movies, traveling

References

Prof. Dr. Mesut Güneş, Chair of Communication and Networked Systems (ComSys), Institute for Intelligent Cooperating Systems, Otto-von-Guericke-University Magdeburg, Germany, email: mesut.guenes@ovgu.de

Dr. Kapal Dev, *Assistant Lecturer*, Munster Technological University, Cork, Ireland, email: kapal.dev@mtu.ie